Everybody, can you hear me?
>> We hear you.
Good. So again, I'm going to decline
requests to record this meeting because
when I approve it, your recording sort
of tends to clash with Zoom's recording
sometimes. And so Zoom doesn't record
the lecture and we end up with
unrecorded lectures.
It's 8 a.m. We'll wait a couple of
minute half a minute
before we begin.
All
right. So, let me begin. I'm going to
continue the series of lectures on
training deep neural networks. What was
the last topic we discussed? Anybody?
Can you remind me what the last topic we
discussed was?
Vector derivatives,
back propagation. We discussed back
propagation, huh? And what did we use
back propagation for?
What did we use back propagation for?
For computing derivatives, for
calculating the gradient that could be
used in gradient descent. So the story
so far we saw that neural networks are
universal approximators. They can model
any odd function provided they have the
right architecture. But we must train
them to approximate our function. For
this, we must specify an architecture
and learn the weights and biases of the
networks. And the networks are trained
to minimize a total loss on a training
set. This is an instance of empirical
risk minimization
and we use variance of gradient descent
to perform this minimization.
The gradient of the error with respect
to network parameters is computed
through back propagation. That's what
you use in gradient descent.
So here is the overall setup. You're
given some training data. You define a
loss which is the total training error
which is the average divergence between
the actual and desired outputs of the
network over all training instances.
This is a function of all network
parameters. For gradient descent, you
initialize these parameters and then you
iteratively
find the derivative of the loss with
respect to these parameters and take a
step against the gradient which is the
transpose of the derivative. You do this
until the loss does not decrease
anymore.
Now the last topic we did was looking at
deriving the entire thing using vector
math. And so a quick recap of that
again, here's what we did in the forward
pass. The output of the network was
remember again to compute the
derivatives, you had to pass the data
through the network in a forward pass in
order to be able to compute all
intermediate variables and then compute
the derivatives going backward from the
end to the beginning. So in the forward
pass the uh data was processed using
just a very simple iteration of two
steps. In the first step at each layer,
you computed an aphine term which was
obtained from the output of the previous
layer. And the rule used to compute this
aine term was that you multiplied the
output of the previous layer the vector
with the output of the previous layer by
the weight matrix for the layer and then
added a bias and then subsequently we
just applied the activation for the
layer. So if the variables here are zk
and uh ykus one
and yk and so if one were to draw the
influence diagram yk minus one which is
this guy here influences zk which is
this guy here and on the edge you would
have the derivative of zk with resp with
respect to yk minus one which is just
the weight matrix.
Then subsequently
you have the output of the k layer and
that is influenced by zk the aine term.
So the next step is that the zk
influences the yk and the weight on the
edge is the derivative of yk with
respect to zk which is just the jacobian
of the activation matrix.
So guys, please do not uh request me for
uh approval, auto approvals because they
disrupt the lecture. They pop up windows
on my screen and then they can actually
kill the recording. Anyway, so does
everybody
recall this? This is the sequence of
influences. Ykus one influences zk,
which in turn influences yk. The
derivative on this edge is just the
weight. The derivative on this edge is
the uh Jacobian of the activation and
eventually of course you get the
divergence. So when you go backwards
assuming you have the derivative of the
divergence with respect to yk
the derivative of the divergence with
respect to zk was just obtained by right
multiplying
this derivative by the jacobian of the
activation. And then taking a step
further back, the derivative with
respect to yk minus one was just
obtained by multiplying the derivative
with respect to zk
which was computed here
by right multiplying it by the by the
weight on top of this edge which is just
the weight matrix. So just uh repeated
iterations of these two steps would keep
driving the derivatives backward through
the [laughter] net. And at each point
the derivative with respect to the
biases at any layer was simply the
derivative with respect to Z. And the
derivative with respect to the weights
was obtained by multiplying the input to
the edge that had the weight ykus one by
the derivative at the output of the edge
which is zk. So does everybody remember
these two equations over here? Everyone
I know the screen is a mess but do you
remember this?
Okay. And so just to ensure that you do
indeed remember this, I'm going to have
a quote. So here is the overall network
training algorithm. We'll initialize all
the weights and biases. Then in the
forward pass, you'd compute the output
for the network and the divergence. And
in the backward pass, you just keep
computing the derivatives with respect
to intermediate variables on and the
network parameters
all the way going backwards. You would
average the derivatives for the
parameters over the training set and
then that average of the derivative is
the is the derivative of the overall
loss with respect to the parameter and
that's what you'd use in gradient
descent. So here is our first poll just
to check if you actually recall the
simple derivatives.
Okay, five seconds, guys.
I'll give you a few more seconds, then
I'll stop this.
Okay, let me stop this.
And what was the answer over here? What
was the answer? A, right? So the
derivative with respect to the weight
is simply the input. Now the weight is
always on an edge which connects ykus
one to zk.
And so the derivative this is so this is
W K and the derivative with respect to
this weight is the input to this edge
times the derivative for the output at
of the edge. So that's this first one
over here with that behind us. Let's
move on. Right.
So unloads
question backdrop. When I say backdrop,
I'm not really referring to backdrop by
itself, but rather to gradient descent
where gradients are computed using
backdrop. Historically, the term
backdrop, although strictly speaking,
should only be used as a reference to
the algorithm that uses that computes
the derivatives. Uh people just said
back prop when they actually meant
gradient descent using gradients derived
through backdrop. So I might also use
the term backdrop to refer to the
overall training algorithm. So the
question is does backdrop always work?
How does it converge? What are the rates
of convergence? What are the
restrictions? So we're going to discuss
all of these in today's class and in the
next class
about how you can make it faster. Are
there alternate approaches and uh how
you can modify them and what what are
the speedups. So over here the last
topic uh this would be the transpose
Jesse the last one. Okay so
let's go on first does backrop always do
the right thing is it always right
assuming that if you perform gradient
descent using derivatives obtained
computed using backrop does it actually
always find the minimum of the
divergence function. So the question is
does gradient descent find the right
solution even if it finds the actual
minimum of the loss. So let me explain
remember this picture where uh I had two
classes the red class and the blue class
and the optimal threshold between the
red and the blue class would be
somewhere here. Right now, if my current
network, if I were using threshold
activations, I might get the uh dotted
line as my classifier. And we saw that
over here, if I just use threshold
activations, moving this dotted line
left or right doesn't really tell me
whether the error has changed. But what
do we really want to optimize the
network for? What we really want to
optimize the network for is
classification error. We must somehow
find the network that performs the
smallest number of errors. But having a
threshold activation network gave us a
situation where you couldn't wiggle the
parameters of the network to determine
if you were going in the right direction
direction or not. So our solution was to
replace this hard threshold activation
by the smooth function. And instead of
simply counting the number of
mclassifications, we said we will count
the total distance between the act
target output and the actual output of
the network. And when we did so, we
found that when so this this over here
t2 is actually to the left of t1. We
found that when we moved the
function left,
this total distance actually reduced.
And so this gave us the indication that
we want to continue moving the function
left.
So this seems to be doing the right
thing. Yes or no? Does it seem to be
doing the right thing?
What do you guys think? Is it guaranteed
to do the right thing every time? What
What do you think?
probably not. Can you give me an
situation where uh it wouldn't do the
right thing?
So,
okay, let me give you an example. Let's
say I have lots and lots and lots lots
of blue dots out here. Like 5 trillion
blue dots out here. They are way out at
the edge. So they are way into the safe
region of the of the class, right? But
then what we are really doing is we're
adding these total distances, this
function doesn't actually go to Z1 or
zero. It just sort of appro as towards
it. Meaning although these points are in
the safe region, each of them
individually has some distance from the
function. And so although each of them
the distance of each of these points
from the function might be
infinitisimally small together they
could account for a whole lot. And so if
the number of points on this side is
small and if the number of points here
is very large these guys will try to
push the function further right so that
their distances can reduce further. And
so in this situation, if I have lots of
rubbish out here, not rubbish, but
training points out here, this training
setup actually encourages the function
to become something like this, which is
entirely wrong.
Do you guys see how this could happen?
Anybody? Any questions?
Do you see how that could happen? Right.
So, and so this error that we've got,
this error is
only a proxy for the actual objective
that we want to minimize, which is the
classification error. This proxy kind of
helps us optimize things, but if your
training data are not the right thing,
even though they are perfectly
classifiable, the training data could
just end up pushing your classifier to
the entirely wrong solution. So here's a
better way of looking at it. So the
question is is backup always right?
Observe that over here the loss function
is the total distance and if if you had
too much data out here then that loss
function is actually minimized by
pushing the function out here.
So what this means is that minimizing
finding the true minimum of the loss
function doesn't necessarily find the
classifier that has the the lowest
classification error. That's right,
Georgina. So uh and so assuming backrop
finds the global minimum of the loss,
does it always find the right solution?
In classification problems, the
classification error is a non-ifferiable
function of the weights. The divergence
function we optimize is only a proxy for
the classification error and minimizing
the divergence may not minimize
classification error. Let's look take a
look at an example here. I have I'm
trying to train a single perceptron. So
this classifier that I'm trying to train
is just a perceptron. Right now I have
data of this kind in two classes. Are
these data linearly separable?
Are these data linearly separable? Yes
or no? Yes. Okay. So if I use the
perceptron classification rule which is
guaranteed to find a boundary if the
data say linearly separable the
perceptron classification rule may find
this boundary.
If I use the proxy method that we saw in
the previous examples and use something
of this kind that too is likely to find
the same solution. So in this case,
regardless of whether you're using the
perceptron rule or the proxy, both of
them will find the same solution. But
now I add one training data instance
from the red class over here. Are the
two classes linearly separable?
Are they linearly separable?
Yes. Right. And so will the perceptron
rule find the se find this uh boundary?
Yes. The perceptron rule is going to
find something like this which actually
separates the two classes. But then if I
use the proxy loss, what happens to the
proxy loss? If I have a ton of data out
here and here, this guy is going to
contribute very very very little to the
overall loss, right? And so if the
original classifier were like so
the contribution of this data point is
only going to make it shift a little bit
like from the dotted line being which is
the original classifier to maybe this
guy. And so you can see how adding the
spoiler over here can completely change
the classifier if I were using the
perceptron rule. But if I'm using the
proxy loss with backdrop it's probably
not going to change the classifier very
much. Similarly, if I have say uh this
guy, if I add this dot as my spoiler,
now there is still a linear classifier
and the perceptron rule would find this
dotted line. But the gradient
descentbased method, this guy is not
going to modify the over overall loss
too much. So, it's probably going to
shift the classifier from the dotted
line to the red line. If I had my
spoiler out here, the perceptron rule is
going to find this boundary. The
gradient descent rule is not going to
change the classifier very much. If I
have the perceptron spoiler out here,
the perceptron rule is going to find
this guy, but the gradient descent
method is going to find this guy. Right?
And so you can see how in every case
although there is a classifier,
the gradient descentbased mechanism is
not guaranteed to find this classifier.
The minimum the actual minimum optimum
of the gradient descent method is in the
wrong place. Can you see how do you guys
see how that works over here? Yes or no?
Right. So, can you give me like a 50
thumbs ups? So, I know I know I can move
on. I have like five.
Okay. Perfect. Right. So, you're getting
it.
So, the perceptron. Now, my question to
you guys is this. Look at the blue line
versus the red line, right? So, the blue
line swings around crazily. The red line
doesn't change a whole lot. Is this
desirable behavior or undesirable
behavior? What do you guys think?
It depends. Depends on what
it's the behavior of the red line. Is
that desirable or undesirable?
It's undesirable. It is desirable. Why?
Because
well the perceptron may change greatly
upon adding just a single instance. It
fits the training data well. It has low
bias meaning if it's possible it makes
no errors. But it has high variance
meaning just by adding one training data
point. I can make the solution change
entirely.
Right? That doesn't happen with the back
prop based rule. It prefers consistency
over perfection. It's a low variance
estimator, meaning you can't just add
one or two data points and make it
completely change its answer. And this
is generally considered a desirable
trait. So although it may not find the
right solution, it turns out that in
many settings it actually gives you a
better solution than the actual solution
that gives you the lowest classification
error. That make sense to everybody?
So the red and blue dots are different
classes you get. Okay.
Okay. So now that's for a single
linearly separable class.
Uh I know u single perceptron trying to
separate linearly separable classes. If
you have classes which have need a more
complex boundary and they need an entire
network, you're going to need an MLP and
the MLP is going to be give you a
boundary of this kind. So
I either say so that the uh bias over
here is the difference between the
classifier that you actually get and the
optimal classifier meaning it's making
an error. The error that you make is the
bias. It prefers to be I give you a
biased answer versus an answer that
swings around crazy. Right? So even if I
have a nonlinear boundary and MLP will
learn a boundary of this kind. If I add
a spoiler over here, it's not going to
just wildly go after something like
this. Let's maybe just change just a
little bit, right? And so back
propagation will often not find a
separating solution even though the
solution is within the class of
functions learnable by the framework.
This is because the separating solution
is not a feasible optimal for the loss
function. But one resulting benefit is
that a backdrop train neural network
classifier has lower variance than an
optimal classifier for the training
data. So that makes sense to everybody.
Just to check that here is my second
point.
Okay, 10 seconds.
All
right.
Let me stop here.
Okay. Does anybody want to answer this
question? What is the question
over here? What is the answer?
Minimizing the differential loss
function of a loss function
will not necessarily necessarily
minimize the classification error.
So this is what we saw. The reason the
answer is false is that as we saw over
here the minimum for the loss isn't
necessarily
uh the solution that actually performs
classification. Remember the linear
classifier this is within the set of
feasible solutions for a perceptron. But
the backdrop based method won't find it.
It will find this one. That's what we
mean. Right?
So
move on. Any questions?
Any questions?
No. Okay. Now, in the example, in the
statements that I assume made earlier, I
assume that the loss objective had a
single global minimum that could be
found. And so, the statement I made
about the variance assumes this global
minimum. But you can also have local
minima like a function like these. There
are many different values where there's
a minimum and gradient descent can find
any of these. So what does the loss
surface actually look like? Uh there's a
lot of math about it, but a lot of the
math seems to indicate that in large
networks, you are likely far more likely
to find saddle points of this kind than
actual local minima. So saddle points
are points where the function decreases
in one direction but increases in the
other direction. There too you'll find a
location where the slope is zero. The
second thing is that for large networks
you get lots of local minima but the
local minima tend to all be more or less
equivalent meaning the value at the
minimum for all of them tends to be very
tend to the values at all these minima
tend to be very close to one another.
This is true for large networks but not
for small networks.
So uh while while it doesn't matter
which local minimum you find so long as
it's large enough uh you certainly don't
want to get stuck in things like saddle
points.
So the story so far neural networks can
be trained they are gradient descent
which minimizes a loss function. Back
prop can be used to derive the
derivatives for the loss. Gradient
descent is not guaranteed to find a true
solution. even if it exists, it's unique
and lies within the capacity of the
network to model because the optimum for
the loss function may not be the true
solution. This was the point we were
trying to make, right? And so for large
networks, furthermore, the loss function
may have a large number of unpleasant
saddle points or local minima. You don't
want to be get get stuck at saddle
points because there too the derivative
tends to be zero. local minimar may be
less of a problem although they are a
problem particularly for small networks
any questions about anything we've done
so far any questions
okay I'm assuming no right so I'm going
to jump into the real meat of today's
lecture in the discussion so far we
assume that the training arrives at a
local minimum but does it always
converge does it get to the local
minimum How long does it take? It's hard
to analyze this for an MLP. But we can
look at the problem through the lens of
convex optimization.
Why convex optimization? Because we know
how to analyze it. So this is what I
like to call the street light effect.
Everybody's familiar with this old joke
where some guy loses his keys in a bar
and the policeman finds him looking for
the keys under a street light. And when
asked why, he says he can't find
anything in the bar anyway. He might as
well look where he can see. So it sounds
silly, but it actually has some uh
there's some logic to the reasoning. If
you analyze what you can understand,
maybe you can carry those lessons over
to things that you can't really
understand. And so we're going to work
on assume things are convex. A surface
is convex if it's continuously curving
upwards. So something like this. One one
way of looking at it is that uh it's
convex if if I take any two points on
the surface and draw a line connecting
the two every point on the line lies
above the surface. It doesn't matter
which two points I take. If I draw a
line connecting the two lines, the line
must lie entirely above the surface.
This kind of surface is called convex.
You can also have now this surface over
here is not convex because if I took
this line point over here and this point
over here and connected them up then
there's this region where the line goes
below the curve. Similarly you can
define a convex set where a set is set
to be convex if when I take any two
points within the set and draw a line
all points of the line fall within the
set. So this set is convex. This set is
convex. This set is not because if I
connect these two guys, this portion of
the line goes outside the set. And
typically, you know, it's it's very easy
to analyze convex functions over convex
sets. That's what we will do. And then
we'll sort of try to transpose those
lessons to the more generic setting.
The second issue that we we want to
think about is convergence.
Now gradient isn't gets to the solution
one step at a time. It's an iterative
algorithm. An iterative algorithm is set
to converge to the solution if the
iterations eventually arrive at a fixed
point where the gradient is zero and
further updates don't change the
estimate. But then you can have behavior
where the algorithm doesn't actually
come to a fixed point but keeps bouncing
around. This is jittering. Or you can
even have a situation where it keeps
getting further and further away. This
is divergence. All three of these things
are going to happen.
So
when do we get these three behaviors? To
understand that, I'm going to start with
analyzing what is probably the most
beautiful convex function possible. In
many ways, it's the ideal convex
function because uh the it has this
property that it curves steeply away
from the optimum. It becomes shallower
close to the optimum. It doesn't become
too shallow. It doesn't become too
steep. Now, if I had something like x
raised to 4, then this function ends up
looking something like so. Much flatter
at the minimum and much steeper at the
optimum far away. Which means that any
gradient descent method is going to take
a lot of time getting to the solution.
The ideal convex function is a
quadratic. So, let's analyze a
quadratic. And a quadratic has this
formula over here which is uh
the variable e= half I'm assuming e is a
function of w. e =/ a w ^2 + bw + c. I
put this half here as a matter of
convenience. Now how would I find the
value of w where this quadratic is
minimum? Anybody? How would I find the
value of w where the quadratic is
minimum? Anybody remember this?
differentiate derivative. It's a
quadratic, right? So, it's a quadratic
and quadratic has a solution - b plus or
minus square roo of b square minus
4 a c over 2 a. Remember,
do you guys remember there's actually a
formula for the minima of quadratics,
right?
Yes. No.
Yes. But yes, differentiation also
works. So there are a couple of
different ways in which I can get the
optimum minimum of this quadratic. I can
do this directly by solving or I could
use gradient descent where I start off
with an initial w and then keep taking
steps
against the derivative. Both are
possible. Right? If I take this
approach,
then what is the step size that gets me
to the solution in the shortest number
of steps?
Can anyone tell me? If I take this
approach, what is the step size eight
that gets me to the solution in the
shortest number of steps?
Anyone?
One. Let's work it out. Okay. And so I'm
going to work it out like so. How many
of you are familiar with the tailaylor
series?
What's the tailaylor series expansion of
a function?
If I have f ofx and if I want to expand
it around some x0
then the tailaylor series expansion
basically says this is equal to f of x0
plus
frime
of x0
* x - x0 right
plus
half of
fprime of x0 by
* x - x0 all squared
+ 1 / 6
fp prime of x0
* x - x0 cub and so on. Do you guys
remember this?
Do you guys remember this?
How many of you remember this? Everybody
must remember this, right? Okay. So, if
I apply this
Taylor series expansion and I take the
expansion around W K, what is this going
to look like? If I take the expansion
around WK, what's it going to look like?
Will it have this third third derivative
term? Will it have this term or will it
stop after just the quadratic term?
Will it have this term? it will not have
this term because a quadratic doesn't
have third and higher derivatives. So
the actual solution is going to be the
quadratic approximation is going to be E
equals
E of
W K, right?
Plus E prime
of W K
W minus W K, right?
plus half of E W prime
W - W K².
You guys agree with this? Yes or no?
Are you guys okay with this formula
here? Yes. Okay. And what is Epime?
Eouble prime is simply going to be A,
right?
So I can replace this half double prime
and just write a
because I'm taking the derivative. The
first derivative is going to be a w + b.
The second derivative is just going to
be a. So are you guys okay with this?
Yes. Now okay. I'm still going to write
e prime
for
uh
I'm just still going to write half of e
double prime for now. Okay. Now, if I
were to differentiate this and equate it
to zero, what do I get? What is the
derivative of this guy?
The derivative of this first term is
simply going to be e prime of wk.
Correct?
Because the derivative of wus w k is 1.
This is just a value. So this will go
away. It's e prime of wk. The derivative
of the second guy is going to be 2 * 2 *
half 2 will cancel plus e prime
* w - wk. Correct?
Yes or no?
Are you guys okay with this formula over
here? This the derivative?
Yes. I'd like to see a few more yeses.
Okay. If I equate it to zero,
then I'm going to get E prime.
So, let me take this guy out here. So
I'm going to say EP
prime inverse
time E prime
plus W - W K
equals Z. Correct?
Are you guys okay with this?
This the second term has not vanished.
I've just differentiated it. Right? This
this term vanished. This is not it's not
a function of W. This this guy just gave
me E prime. This guy gave me Epime* W1 W
- WK. So if you're okay with this, this
gives me the solution W star equals W K
minus
Epime inverse
E prime.
Right?
So this is the solution correct? Yes or
no?
Yes or no? Okay. And so if this is a
solution then comparing it with this
iterative solution over here.
Is there a step size? Okay. Does this
look like this guy? Do this and this
look the same
right? Do this and this look the same.
If you had E prime
plus Epime*
W minus W K.
So if I premultiply by E prime E prime
inverse this goes out here. That's what
happens. That answer your question.
Okay. So do these two look the same?
Yes or no? Right. So the inverse of the
derivative second derivative is the
optimal aim. If you if your step size is
the inverse of the second derivative
which is just going to be a inverse then
you'll get from here to here in a single
step. That make sense to everybody?
Yes. No.
Okay. So given that this is basically
all I'm saying if I write this in Taylor
series I can write as E of W K * E prime
* W minus W K plus/ E W primer prime * W
- WK^ 2 so if I take the derivative I
find that the optimal that W min is W K
minus E prime inverse * E prime
comparing it to these two I find that
the optimal step size Bruno we'll get
there right is when it's the second
inverse of the second derivative which
is a inverse. So what happens if I'm out
here and I'm using this iterative
formula, right? If I take the optimal
step size, I'm going to get to the
solution in one step. Yes or no?
Yes or no?
Okay. What if I take a step size that's
less than half the optimal step size?
Then what happens if I take a step size
that's less than the optimal step size?
Then what happens?
Can someone tell me? I'm going to take
several steps, right? But I'm going to
get there in one sequence. If I take a
step that's greater than the optimal
step size, what happens?
I'm going to jump across. But the next
time I'm going to jump ac across here,
and I'm going to do this, right?
Yes. No.
Yeah. It's going to bounce it. Okay. Is
there a step size where it will actually
go out?
Instead of coming down, it goes up.
What will happen?
Is there a step size? What if I take a
step size that is twice the optimal step
size? Where will I go from here? Twice
the optimal step size. level.
Anybody?
I'm for twice the optimal step size. I'm
going to go exactly over here. The next
step, I'm going to come back here. I'm
going to keep bouncing back and forth
at twice the optimal step size, right?
Yes or no?
And if it's more than twice the optimal
step size, then I'm actually going to go
out of the curve.
Right? That clear to everybody?
So at twice the optimal step size,
you'll keep bouncing around. You'll
you'll neither converge nor diverge.
Less than twice the optimal step size,
you will converge. At the optimal step
size, you'll get there in one step. More
than twice the optimal step size, you're
going to go away. That's the lesson you
want to keep. And now for a generable
generic differentiable convex function,
you can always write a second order
approximation as a quadratic. And then
the optimal step size is always going to
be the inverse of the second derivative.
Except now you'd have to keep doing it
iteratively. So if you do took a
quadratic approximation over here, it
would be something like this. Your
optimal step size would come here. Then
you're going to take another quadratic
approximation over here and do it again
and keep doing you keep coming up with
second order approximations and use the
optimal step size in each case. That's
Newton's method. But we're not worried
about Newton's method. We're worried
about convergence and divergence. So
that was for a scalar function. But now
let me consider a function something
that's a function of two variables. say
f of w1 w2.
So if it's a function of two variables
as simple way to write this it's
quadratic. I can write it as half
uh erase this here. I can write this as
half. Oh, come on. Half of
a1
w1 squared
plus b1
w1.
I'll ignore the cross term for now. It
doesn't really make a difference. +/ of
a2
w2
plus b2
w2 plus c. So does everybody see that
this is a quadratic function of two
variables? This guy here. Yes or no?
Okay. So if this is a quadratic function
of two variables, what does it look
like? If this is w1
and if this is w2 and if I draw the
equal value low side meaning uh if I
make the plot of all the w1 w2
combinations at which the function value
is the same then the equal value loi end
up looking like this. They're all going
to look like ellipses. Do you agree with
this picture?
Yes or no? Yeah. Okay. So if they look
like so then
what we are going to find is this.
If I look consider any one direction. So
this is like saying if I fix W1 for
different values of W1
this term
ends up being different. So if I keep
changing W1, right,
it's still a quadratic in W2, but this
additive term changes. So at different
W1 values, if I slice the function, I'm
going to get different quadratics in W2
and all of them will have the minimum at
the same point. Yes, the darker values
are lower values. So
do you do you agree with this?
Right. Okay. So similarly if I fix the
W2
for different values of W2
I'm going to get as a function of W1 I'm
going to get the same quadratic it's
just that the heights will differ right
these are w1 and w2
okay so for different values of w2 as a
function of w1 I get different
quadratics and so the same they Only
difference will be the heights. All of
them will have the optimum at the same
point basically out here. So are you
guys okay with this?
Yes. No.
Okay.
And so I can look at the two quadratics
independently. For the first one, I have
a quadratic which is half a1 w + b b1 w1
plus some bunch of terms which don't
affect the position of the optimum. For
the second one, for w2, it's half a2 w2
squared plus b2 w2 plus some terms that
don't affect the position of the
optimum. So in the xaxis,
the optimal step size is a1 inverse. In
the yaxis, the optimal step size is a2
inverse. These two need not be the same.
Do you see this?
Yes or no?
Okay. So what can happen when this
happens? Right? So consider this. When I
use gradient descent, I use this
formula. I use the for this formula uses
the same step size for every variable.
Right? But then if I look at this curve,
this these ellipses are narrower in the
horizontal direction. They are broader
in the vertical direction. Which means
in the horizontal direction the curve
looks like this. In the vertical
direction the curve looks like this.
Right?
Which has the
what is is the optimal step size for
this guy smaller or greater than the
optimal step size for this one? What do
you think?
What is the is the optimal step size for
this one smaller or greater? It's going
to be small, right? The optimal step
size here will be small. For this one,
it will be big. So now let's say I take
start off at this point. Okay. And let's
say I take a step size.
That step size is optimal for this guy.
meaning it's optimal in this direction.
What will happen to this?
If it's optimal in this direction, then
it means that it's going to come from
here to here in one step. But here it
can actually begin diverging. So the
resultant solution is going to look
something like this. Right?
Yes. No.
Right. On the other hand, that makes
sense to everybody.
That makes sense to everybody. Okay. So
on the other hand, if I go by the
optimal step size of this, what will
happen?
What happens if I go by the optimal size
for this guy?
That too slow for this one, right? So
it's going to take oh
to get here and so you have this problem
you have this tension right so the
optimal step size can be different for
different directions the optimal step
size in one direction cause even can
even cause divergence in the other here
I have an example in the vertical
direction the optimal step size is one
in the horizontal direction the optimal
step size is 33 here the step size I've
taken in the first example is 2.1
times the optimal step size for the
second direction. So it's small enough
that it will converge in the first
direction, but it's going to diverge in
the second direction. And so you can see
what happens to the solution. In the
second picture, it's exactly twice the
optimal step size for the horizontal
direction. So it it's 66. It's still
small enough to converge in the vertical
direction. It converges in the vertical
direction but in the horizontal
direction keeps bouncing around. Right
here it's 1.5 times the optimal step
size for this
horizontal direction which means it's
going to converge in both directions.
Although in the horizontal direction
because it's 1.5 it's going to keep
crossing back and forth before it comes
to a solution.
This guy is the optimal step size in the
horizontal direction, but then it takes
forever in the vertical direction. So
you see what's happening over here. Do
these pictures make sense to you guys?
So Georgina, the optimal step size for
the narrow one is going to be smaller,
right? Because it's steeper. So any
questions about this example? And what
is the lesson you got from this guy from
these from these pictures? Anybody? What
is the lesson we got?
anyone
what we want is that the learning rate
must be lower than twice the smallest
optimal learning rate for any component
otherwise the learning will diverge but
this can make the learning rate very
slow because for other directions it may
be too slow right for the third image
this guy I'm using 2.1 1.5 times the
33 right so in the horizontal direction
it's going to be doing this and slowly
converging in the vertical direction is
converging smoothly that's what it means
so moving on right so the
>> a vector we'll get to that right vector
so here we have uh again for generic
differentiable multivaried functions the
same principles hold I can now just take
second order tailaylor series
approximations Everything that we saw
still holds except that we're going to
be looking at the igen vector igen
values of the Hessen matrix which gives
you the uh quadratic coefficient in each
direction. There's a bunch of stuff on
the slides. I'll skip that. But then
convergence what we see is no the factor
of two is always the case right the
factor two is for any quadratic. So
convergence behaviors
become increasingly unpredictable as
dimensions increase because this range
is going to be uh it's going to be very
hard to get the the steepest and the
shallowest directions to line up for the
fastest convergence. Ideally the
learning rate must be close to both the
largest optimal learning rate and the
smallest optimal learning rate. So if
the ratio of the largest and the
smallest optical learning rates is
large, this is like like a condition
number, the convergence is going to be
really really slow. I have a bunch of
hidden slides that talk a lot more about
this. But here is the issue, right? That
we want
we want to make the step size such that
it works for every direction while at
the same time not being too slow. Right?
So we just the analysis we saw was based
on trying to ensure that the step size
is not so large as to cause a divergence
within a convex region like so. Right?
So everybody agree with this? Yes.
Okay. If you use a vector learning rate,
is it going to be gradient descent?
Guys, if each direction has a different
learning rate, is it going to be
gradient descent?
Yes or no? What do you think?
The gradient is a vector. Correct?
So you are actually going along the
vector. If each direction each
component has a different learning rate,
then you're scaling the different
components directly. So the resulting
direction in which you will walk is
going to be something other than
gradient descent. It's not going to be
gradient descent. Right? So that there
in lies the issue when we decide to go
by the direction of steep head steepest
descent you end up with these issues.
But then is it really a bad thing? Now
go back here is your loss function. Your
loss function is going to look something
like this. If your initial estimate is
over here, do you want it to converge to
this point or do you want it to
initially diverge and find a better
value? Do you really want this? You want
it to diverge, right? But then
divergence is bad. So what is your
solution?
What is the dissolution over here?
Clearly you want it to diverge. But if
it keeps diverging, you're never going
to ever get to a solution. So what's the
solution?
Anybody?
Diverge and reduce the step size.
Exactly. So what we really want to do is
start off with a large learning rate.
it's large enough to cause a divergence,
then keep reducing it. And it just so
happens that good minima tend to be in
big bowls. And so eventually you're
going to end up in a big bowl where the
learning rate is small enough that even
if you initially diverge a bit, you're
going to end up
the learning rate is eventually going to
catch up with the bowl and you get to
the bottom. So the correct thing for us
to do is always to start off with a
large learning rate for us to escape
local minima of the bad kind and keep
decreasing it so that you eventually
find a large goal
to whose bottom you will get. That make
sense to everybody? Yes. No.
>> Right. So can I see a few more thumbs
ups before I move on because we're going
to get to the difficult portion of the
lecture. Okay. Right. And so typically
how do you deal? So this we call this uh
it will stay in large values sonic but
the in general large values tend to be
better lower minimum. That's a property
of functions. So that's a good thing. So
this will actually help us find large
values.
Now this is what we call a decaying
learning rate. You start with a large
learning rate and then keep reducing it
at every step. And there are many
strategies for it where the kth step
your k learning rate is the initial
learning rate divided by k minus one or
by k minus one squared or you can reduce
the learning rate exponentially with
iterations. A more common approach is to
start with a fixed learning rate until
the loss stagnates and then the learning
rate and keep doing this until things
converge. So any questions?
Any questions?
No. So the story so far, gradient
descent can miss obvious answers, but
this may be a good thing. Convergence
issues abound. The loss surface has many
saddle points, although perhaps not so
many bad local minima. Gradient descent
can stagnate on saddle points. So
that's right. That's what schedules are.
So vanilla gradient descent may not
converge or may converge too slowly. The
optimal learning rate for one component
may be too high or too low for others.
So let's get to poll number
two
book.
So let me end the poll
and
does anybody want to give me the answer?
What is the answer? One, right?
One. Is this one? I said mark all two
statements. Is the second statement true
or false?
Okay, so only the first statement is
true.
And so the story so far divergence
causing learning rates may not be a bad
thing particularly for ugly loss
functions. Decaying learning rates
provide good a good compromise between
escaping or local minima and
convergence. But many of the convergence
issues arise because we are doing
gradient descent which forc us to have
the same learning rate for all
parameters. Now one way to get around it
is to find the uh quadratic coefficient
for every direction and then optimize
using the quadratic coefficient for
every direction. But that's very very
very expensive because computing the
second derivative in large networks is
going to take an enormous amount of
time. So we can do this right and so
we need to take a step back. The
problems arise because we want a fixed
step size across all dimensions. They're
tied to the gradient. I'm going to try
to release this but I'm going to do this
in a way in which I'm trying to I will
instead of trying to find this
mathematically we try to track the
optimal learning rate for each direction
using some other heristic. Again,
ideally the way you would do it is for
each direction this is going to be uh
you know proportional to LP prime
inverse right for each component. But
then this is impossible to compute for
anything except the tiniest functions.
And so we can't do this. And so we're
going to have to find some other
solutions. That making sense what I just
said?
Yes or no? Okay. So let's see how we do
this. Right. We're going to have
algorithms that use derivative
information for trends but don't follow
them absolutely. So we have two sets of
two techniques on the slides. One is R
prop, one is quick. These are not
derivative based algorithms but
derivative inspired algorithms. Let's
look at R prop first called resilient
propagation. It's a very simple
algorithm that's followed independently
on each component. At each time, if the
derivative at the current location
recommends going continuing in the same
direction as before, meaning if the
derivative at this iteration has the
same sign as the derivative at the
previous iteration, you increase the
step. If the derivative has changed
sign, it means we've overshot a minimum.
We reduce the step size and reverse
direction. Let's do this with pictures.
Let's say I have a function of this
kind. I start over here. I compute the
derivative. The derivative is negative.
So it's recommending that I must take a
step forward. So I take a step forward
and I come here. Then I compute the
derivative over here. The derivative is
still negative. So it's still
recommending that I go forward, which
means I'm doing the right thing. So now
I'm going to increase my step size by a
factor alpha. So the next is because I'm
encouraged when I'm going forward,
right? And so I increase my step size
and take my next step, which is alpha *
w. And then I check my derivative again.
It's still negative. I'm only looking at
the sign of the derivative, mind you,
which tells me I'm still going in the
right direction. So now I'm going to
multiply the previous step
by another alpha, scale it up, and take
an even larger step.
I keep doing this, but eventually what
will happen? At some point my step size
is so large I'm going to overshoot the
minimum. If I overshoot the minimum,
what should I do? Any suggestions?
If I overshoot it, what should I do?
Reduce.
I go back
and then reduce that step size by a
factor beta and then take and that's my
new step. Right?
So that make sense? Very simple
technique
and you're just going to be keeping
track of the step size in each direction
independently.
Very simple technique and it's going to
find the minimum more often than not. So
I mean even gradient descent will get
you to local minimum. So that's not
really an efficient. It turns out that R
prop is so when I overshoot I'm going to
go back
here
and then reduce the step size and I'm
going to keep doing that eventually I'm
going to find the minimum. So this it
turns out sometimes the step size is
going to be so large that you may
actually escape some local minima and
fall into a deeper valley. So our prop
will often find a better solution than
vanilla gradient is set. That make
sense?
>> Yes. Okay. So give me
guys.
Okay. So
uh
so this is uh the simple R prop
algorithm. Here is pseudo code for that
for R prop. You still need backdrop.
Uh no it's not going to cause the
derivative to change signs. Right? So
look if I have something of this kind
if I have a function of this kind
if the step size over here is very large
I may overshoot but then actually end up
in a bigger value bigger values will
usually trap it but this is t this tends
to overshoot small values that answer
your questions Sean
yes or no okay so that's what see pseudo
code for rrop so Rrop is going to use
you need to check the sign of the
derivative. For that you need to compute
derivatives and usually also have
ceilings and floors on step sizes. So
because we need to compute these
derivatives, you still need to perform
back propagation to compute the
derivatives such that you can find their
sum. So that's our problem. It's a very
remark very simple remarkably simple
first order algorithm that's frequently
much more efficient than gradient
descent and can even be competitive
against more advanced second order
methods. It makes minimal assumptions
about the loss function. You're not
making any assumptions about convexity.
So, and it is still more efficient than
many of the fancy algorithms that we
have these days. So, here is your third
point.
Okay, 10 seconds, guys.
5 seconds.
Is that a very easy question
right? Let me end this right here.
So what is the answer?
Right. RO will revert to the earlier
estimate and take a smaller step. So to
answer the question of why do we not use
R prop all the time? That's going to
come in the next few minutes and in in
the next class. So there's an
alternative to it called quick bra which
actually tries to compute the second
derivative but the second derivative is
not computed rigorously by taking a
derivative but looking at the difference
in steps between adjacent iterations and
that tends to be very efficient also.
It's invented by our own Scott Fman and
it's still one of the fastest training
algorithms for many problems. It's on
the slides. So the story so far,
gradient descent can miss obvious
answers. This may be a good thing.
Vanilla gradient descent may be too slow
or unstable due to the differences
between dimensions. Second order methods
can normalize the variation across
dimensions but are complex. Adaptive or
decaying learning rates can improve
convergence and methods that decouple
the dimensions can improve convergence.
But let's look at this slightly
differently. Right?
So look at this over here. Let's look at
this example and look at the derivatives
in each direction. So this is the x
direction. This is the y direction. So
the so in the y direction the
derivatives are positive positive
positive positive. Right? You keep
coming down in the x direction. What do
the derivatives look like?
What are the what do they look like?
Right? Can somebody tell me?
What do the derivatives look like in the
x direction?
It's going to be positive. Then the next
thing is negative. Right? Then the next
thing is positive and the next thing is
negative. The next thing is positive.
The next thing is negative. By looking
at these guys, can you tell me which
direction I'm actually converging
smoothly in? in which direction I'm
bouncing around?
Can you tell me by looking at these
guys?
Why? Right. So, is there something I can
do about this?
Here is what h I know that here I'm
always doing the right thing. Here I'm
going back and forth. What if I take an
average of all of these derivatives?
I will still get the same thing over
here. What will happen if I take the
average of all of these guys? What would
happen?
What would happen
guys?
The positives and the negatives are
going to kind of cancel each other.
You're going to end up with something
very small. It may not be zero, but it's
going to be small because the positives
and the negatives are going to cancel
each other. Right? So, instead of
directly using these derivatives, why
don't I use these averages? If I use the
averages, then I'm going to actually end
up some doing something like this,
right?
Yes or no?
What do you guys think?
Right. And so this is
the method of
the momentum method, right? You keep
track of the derivatives in individual
directions. Emphasize steps and
directions that converge smoothly.
shrink steps in directions that bounce
around and so I want to take an average
but an average is a problematic thing so
I'm going to use a running average I
maintain a running average of all the
past steps and in the directions in
which I always keep getting a positive
you know the derivative in the same
direction the running average is going
to give me something significant in
directions where they keep flipping sign
the running average is going Give me
give me something small.
This making making sense to all of you
guys?
Yes. No. Yes. Okay. And what is a
standard formula for the running average
of a series? If I've got X1, X2 blah
blah blah, what is the running average?
I can say xbar
after seeing k iterations k observations
is the same as some alpha * xar k -1
plus x k this is the standard procedure
for the running average right you have a
sequence of values so when when I see
the next one the running average of the
whole lot is going to be the running
average of this set scaled down
plus this guy. Right? This is the
standard formula for the running
average. Do you guys remember this? Yes.
No.
It's easy enough to prove this.
Do you want me to prove this? It's easy.
Okay. Let me show you how this works,
right? So the average is 1 / k. Right. X
k Xar k is 1 / k
sine of summation
x i i i i = 1 to k right.
So xar
k + 1
= 1 / k + 1
summation i
x i i i going from 1 to k + 1. I can
rewrite this as 1 / k + 1
k / k + 1
times 1 / k
summation i = 1 to k x i
+
1 / k + 1 x k + 1.
These two are the same formula.
Can you see that? I've just pulled out
the first k term separately and then
I've added the k + one term separately.
Can you guys see that these two are the
same thing?
Right? And this is just xar k. So this
ends up looking like alpha * xar k
plus some
beta * xk + 1. Right? This is the
formula. This is the formula for the
running estimate running average. Yes.
Yes or no?
Do you agree with this guys?
Okay, so that's what we are going to
use. We're going to say
we are going to maintain a running
average of the gradients and it uses the
same formula as before. The running
average of the gradient of the
derivatives computed actually the
gradients, right? The running average of
the gradient is going to be the running
average of the gradient at the previous
step plus the latest gradient step. But
the gradient step is simply as we as we
know minus 8 times the the current
derivative. And then you're going to
always update your parameters using the
running average. This make sense?
This is just the formula we just saw.
Is this making sense? Yes or no? This is
your standard gradient step when you're
not maintaining running averages. What
we are doing is that we're maintaining a
running average of these gradient steps
and updating using using the running
average.
So can I get a few yeses that this made
sense?
I got like a half a dozen
maybe
like a few more.
Okay.
So,
how does that behave? If you were just
doing doing plain gradient descent, see
how this bounces around in the vertical
direction but proceeds smoothly in the
horizontal direction with momentum. This
is called the momentum method. The
gradient has momentum. Then it actually
oscillates less in the vertical
direction and goes to the optimum even
faster. And so uh there's pseudo code
for this. You're going to you're going
to compute the gradient, but then you
use the gradient to actually compute a
running average. And this running
average is what you use to update your
parameter.
Okay.
So, so far so good.
Can I improve on this? This is the
gradient descent method. This is the
momentum method. I'm maintaining a run I
maintain a running average and then
update using the running average. So
what are we actually doing here? So I
have a current step
then at the next iteration
at this current location I'm finding the
gradient right this gradient is being
found at the current location. So this
is my gradient descent step right and
then to this I am adding a scaled
version
beta times this previous step. So the
momentum method takes from the current
step it takes a step against the
gradient over here and then adds a
scaled version of the previous step and
this gives us the final step and this is
where you end up with a solution. This
picture makes sense to all of you guys
what we just did.
Does this picture make sense to all of
you?
Okay. So the step was from here you
first took a gradient step.
You first took a gradient step and then
added the scaled version of the previous
iteration.
It turns out you can change the order.
So momentum steps are computed in two
stages. First we take a step against the
gradient. Then we add a scaled version
of the previous step. This can be made
more optimal by reversing the order of
the procedure. up. So let's say this is
my previous step. Instead of taking a
gradient step over here first, I will
take a scaled version of the previous
step and then take a gradient step over
here. That's going to end up that's
going to give me a final solution over
here. So did this did the difference
between the two things come across?
In the momentum method, we first took a
step here and then took a scaled
version. Here you took a scale version
of the previous step. Here we extended
it by a scaled version of the previous
step and then went against the gradient.
Make sense?
Why is that faster? It's provably
faster. This is called Nsteros method
and this is known to for convex
functions. This is in fact the fastest
way to get to the solution. There's a
very nice paper about it by by a guy
called Nastro obviously and I tried
reading the paper and understanding it
and uh the very first statement in the
paper said obviously and threw a
mathematical statement at me. So I
stared at that obvious statement for
something like three days then gave it
to my student who has won the math who's
won the silver gold medals in the
international math Olympia and he stared
at it for half a day before he came back
and explained it to me. So I can't
really tell you how this is optimal, but
it's provably optimal, right? So,
but the pictures will make sense. Look
at this. This is
this up this upper step. You take a step
against the gradient and then take a
step which is proportional to this guy.
Whereas here, you take a step that's
proportional to this guy and then take a
step against the gradient. And you can
see how the second one is
uh so much
more so much faster visually, right? And
so uh the uh this nestro's accelerated
gradient is an improvement on the
momentum method which actually gets to
the solution much faster. So here is a
training uh round with meros method as
before you compute a gradient but then
the the uh the approach changes at each
step you first extend w by a step that's
a scaled version of the previous step
and then you compute the gradient and
then extend it further against the
gradient. Of course, for all of this you
have to so and then of course you keep
track of what the what the overall
update was. So this is Nestto's
um accelerated
gradient. Now the pictures should make
it very obvious. So if you go back and
look at uh the pseudo code, it should
all make sense. So momentum and
trendbased methods these look at the
historical trend of how of the steps we
have taken to decide the latest step.
We'll get to this topic. We'll return to
this topic again in the next class. But
before that man won one final call.
Okay, I'll stop this in 5 seconds.
Okay, let me end the poll. What do you
guys think?
What is the answer?
If you have you're maintaining a running
average, if the function is constant,
right, then the slope at each point is
constant, is it not? Yes or no?
Yes or no?
Will the running average of these slopes
be any different than the individual
slope?
So
will momentum methods converge faster?
No, because the running average and the
individual slopes are the same. Right?
So momentum methods get you no benefit
on constant slope functions.
That make sense?
Yeah. The step size is the same. You're
just maintaining the running average.
That's it. Right? So this is correct.
And so the story so far, gradient
descent can miss obvious answers. This
may be a good thing. Vanilla gradient
descent may be too slow or unstable due
to the differences between dimensions. I
have not spoken about second order
methods but they normalize variation
across dimensions by scaling the the
space. They are complex adaptive or
decaying learning rates can improve
convergence. Methods that decouple the
dimensions can improve convergence but
then it's hard to figure out what the
optimal step size in each side is going
to be. So you need heristics. Momentum
methods which emphasize directions of
steady improvement are demonstrabably
superior to other methods. So that's the
end of it. Coming up we'll talk about
incremental updates. We'll revisit trend
algorithms and some generaliz look at
generalization and some tricks of the
trait in the next two classes. So, let
me stop the recording
and uh